hey what's up guys my name is the churno
welcome back to my c plus plus series so
far in this sequel
series we've been mostly learning about
various individual language constructs
and just things that we can do in the
language
and how the language itself works but
now it's time to take that and actually
put it into practice and the way that
we'll be doing that
is by learning about how to write our
own data structures
now just to be clear by data structures
i'm talking about things like arrays
lists sets maps trees that kind of stuff
whilst the c plus plus standard template
library comes with
most of these data structures already
implemented for you
i think it's very valuable to try and
write your own because apart from
learning more deeply about how these
data structures actually
work and why they might be more useful
than other data structures
you'll also learn a lot about the
language having to write kind of
efficient versions of these data
structures
along with data structures another
really important part of
programming is of course the patterns or
the algorithms
that will operate upon the data inside
these data structures and that's stuff
that we'll be covering as part of this
series
a little bit later on so today we're
going to be starting with talking about
arrays
and we're going to be creating a very
very simple array just a
static kind of stack allocated fixed
size
array something that can hold a certain
amount of elements of data contiguously
and something that will be easy for us
to interface with and use
as a programmer using that array this is
basically going to be the standard
array class that is provided to us by
the stl in my experience looking through
people's code particularly people who
are
quite new to language or learning the
language even some people who have been
using the language for a long time
this is not something that a lot of
people use a lot of people jump into
using vectors
straight away because they're dynamic
they're resizable they're great aren't
they
well they are but they're also allocated
on the heap and that can tremendously
slow down your program for no reason
because in a lot of cases
you could have gotten away with using a
fixed size static array
no problem and by doing so in the right
places you can greatly speed up the
efficiency
of your program so i think this is
definitely something that you should not
underestimate and later when we get into
algorithms and
stuff like search algorithms we can
greatly improve the performance of our
program
by keeping our memory local on the stack
instead of continually going to the heap
as you'll see in the future but first
before we jump into actually writing
this
i want to thank skillshare for
sponsoring this video
i've been working with skillshare for
quite a while in this channel as you've
probably noticed because i think it's a
really great platform it's a platform
where you can go to to learn a new skill
and it's especially useful when you
don't have a lot of time the thing is
skillshare has a lot of courses they
have
they have courses on pretty much
anything you can think of and they're
all really concise and well put together
and they don't contain a lot of flop
they don't waste your time they just
teach you what you need to know
and usually they're extremely high
quality i love the fact that skillshare
has a lot of videos about things like
productivity things like
marketing i love their art related
courses and especially
this one about how you can relax and
just take a break
with art sometimes the programming gets
overwhelming sometimes you don't
understand something and being able to
find a different creative medium in
which to express yourself and also relax
i think
is really really cool skillshare comes
in at less than ten dollars per month
for an annual subscription
and the first 1000 people who sign up
using my link in the description below
of this video
will get two months of free skillshare
premium that's two months to learn
something
you should be able to learn a lot of
things in those two months and i expect
you to so thank you skillshare once
again for sponsoring this video and
hooking you guys up
with some free learning if you need to
learn something other than c
plus or programming definitely check out
skillshare in the description
below and speaking of learning let's
learn how to write a
fixed size stack allocated array data
structure
in c plus so just to be clear here what
we're trying to create
is a stack allocated array that means an
array that exists on the stack not the
heap
let's start off with the most basic
example of this where we don't have a
class or any kind of helper functions
whatsoever
i'll create an integer array here i'll
call it array and i'll give it the size
of five
we now have a very simple stack
allocated array this is what forms the
basis of this entire data structure
a heap allocated array would look
something like this i'll call it heavy
a the key difference here is that we're
actually using the new keyword this
means that this memory allocation
occurs on the heap and we're explicitly
using a pointer to address it that part
isn't as much different because we can
also use a pointer
to address this array but the main
difference here is that this is
allocated on the heap
as such it's actually possible to
dynamically allocate this meaning that
the size does not have to be specified
at compile time this is not the case
with a stack allocated array where we
need to specify the size at compile time
so
in other words i could have a size
variable here that could be taken in
from anywhere
and then i can simply use that size
variable in this allocation
i cannot do this with my stack allocated
array you can see that gives us an error
this has to be a constant that is known
at compile time because the size of this
memory allocation
on the stack has to be known by the
compiler the other big difference of
course is that with a heap allocated
array like this
we need to make sure that we properly
delete it this is not the case for a
stack allocated array
as it will simply get removed when the
stack frame is
popped which in this case will happen at
the end of this function here i'm not
really going to talk about the benefits
of a stack allocated array like this
versus a heap allocated array as well as
all of the drawbacks
the point is that in a lot of cases if
you're just allocating memory for a
single scope
it's a lot better to use a stack
allocated array just simply because that
memory will be right there on the stack
there's no need for any heap allocations
any kind of indirection everything is
right there available for you and in a
lot of cases this can
greatly improve the performance of your
program so before we create a data
structure that essentially
wraps this and makes it a lot more
usable for us let's take a look at what
the c
standard library provides for us which
is this standard array which is
available since c
plus 11. i'll create this standard array
here with the name collection and i will
also add in the required include here
which is array that's where this
class is actually contained the way that
we use this is primarily using template
arguments so using templates we're able
to specify
the type here as well as the size so
it's interesting to note here that the
size is something that we specify as a
template argument
now if we actually open this array file
here by just going to the document
you can see the entire implementation
because this is completely a templated
class the entire
implementation has to be inside this
header file it can't be compiled into
some kind of library in fact the entire
cpus plus standard template library is
actually in header files because it's
made out of templates
so we'll be referring to this quite a
bit just to see how they do things
whilst also writing our own that is
going to look a lot more simple
than what we have here because the c
plus libraries are usually written
in a not very readable way once we've
got that the primary benefit here is
that we can in fact
easily check what the size is of the
array we can easily obtain an
iterator to the array so in other words
if i wanted to iterate through
every single integer inside this
collection i have a very easy way to do
this
i can also use a traditional for loop
here like so and then
simply use it as if it was any other
array by like printing the value or
doing something like this
doesn't really matter this is basically
what the api for this standard array
class looks like and that's what we'll
be creating today
okay so now that we've done a little bit
of research let's dive in and take a
look at how we can make this ourselves
what i want to do is start with the
first iteration of this how do we do
this
just templates aside the simple kind of
beginner's version
of having a stack allocated array that
is wrapped inside a class well i'll make
a class called array and then i'm going
to decide what kind of type of data this
array is going to hold so we'll go with
an integer
i'll now make an actual stack allocated
array here with a particular size
now this is where our problem comes in
we can't really simply make a
constructor here
that takes in a size like this because
if we did that we would have to somehow
allocate this memory it's not going to
be possible to do this for the same
reason why i can't have an array over
here
that is initialized by a particular
variable like this
you just can't do that because this is
not a constant expression it's not
something that is known at compile time
so we can't have an array whose size is
specified at
runtime so in other words we need to
actually insert a
number into here and this is
specifically where it gets difficult
because if we're trying to do something
like this
how do we control this how can i at the
time of instantiating this class and
using it
how can i tell it how big i want my
static array to be that's why
the standard array class uses a template
now as a side note i just want to
mention that yes i did say that
technically you cannot have a stack
allocated array with a dynamic size
that's not strictly true because it is
possible to allocate memory on the stack
dynamically
we can do that by turning this into a
pointer and then simply saying that m
data is equal to
endpointer allocate size allocate is a
function that lets us allocate memory on
the stack this would successfully
allow us to instantiate our array here
with an actual runtime value here so
this could be of course
a variable that was set to something and
you can see that it works here fine
because this just takes in an integer
and we're allocating the right thing now
there are certain
caveats to using allokay whilst this
memory is technically allocated on the
stack
the compiler doesn't really know how big
the size will be that can lead to
problems and also lack of compiler
optimization so technically speaking you
probably want to avoid lk especially in
this
instance i definitely won't tell you to
avoid allocate in life in general just
because it is extremely useful and it
can definitely benefit the performance
of your program but it's totally
outside of the scope of this tutorial so
we're not going to talk about it here at
all so going back to this
what are our options if we simply have a
declaration like this
and the only thing we can really do is
by using a template unless we want to
have a fixed
size array which means that we just have
a size of 10 and that is just like
this is my array that is 10 integers
large or something like that which is
ridiculous
we need to template this so it's really
easy to write this if you're new to
templates check out my video in the top
right corner about templates but all we
really have to write here is template
size t
and we'll call it s now this can be
you can write this as an int usually in
c plus if you're referring to sizes you
want to use the size t
that's certainly what the entire library
uses for all of the like c plus plus
internal stuff okay so now that we've
got that we can simply replace this 10
with the size
and now if we work to create this array
instead of having to write this size
here what we need to do is specify a
size
like 5 as part of the type so now we
have a templated class meaning a new
version of this class will physically be
created by the compiler with our
argument
every time we create a new array type
okay cool so now that we've got a
dynamic
ish size going on here it's not really
dynamic we still have to specify this at
compile time
there's no way for us to do something
like this at least unless it's a
constant expression but we're not really
going to talk about that
here right now we still have to write
the size of our array up front
during the compilation time like this
which is usually fine because of course
if we're making sac
allocated arrays anyway we just simply
write the size
and so we're used to that that's fine
that's what a fixed size stack allocated
array is all about which is what this
data structure is so now how do we make
this not specific to integers well we
just need to add another template
argument
so i'll write in type name t at the
front of this so we have two arguments
here
type name t which is going to be the
actual type of data that we store
and then size t s which is going to be
the number of
elements that we have here or the count
so over here instead of
int i'm going to replace this with t so
now what happens is when i make this
array i need to specify
the type first and then the actual size
so what this will do is create a version
of this class
which has t set to an int and size set
to five
and this is the class that i end up with
when i compile this template okay cool
so now that i've got that let's take a
look at some of the more useful features
we can actually add to this class
because at the moment it's literally
just a wrapper over what we could have
done without the class anyway
now one of the most useful things that
we can do here is actually keep track of
this size so i can have a function here
that returns the size
i'll just call it size i'll label it as
const here because it's not going to
modify this class and it's just going to
return
s now this is interesting because keep
in mind we're not actually storing the
size anyway there is no additional
variable here called
size which is like set to 5 or set to a
value that we take in in the constructor
during runtime
there is no storage for this whatsoever
what this
actually is is just this templated
argument meaning that when this
actually when this template actually
gets created this s gets replaced with
five so we literally have a function
whose sole job is to return a constant
value of 5 and that's it
there's no additional storage and that's
one of the cool things about this class
as well and by using templates
we're able to actually hard code this
particular function these particular
machine instructions to just simply
return 5
every time which is super nice because
we're not using additional memory to
store
that now this is great because it lets
us actually check the size of this array
we can now
call data.size and immediately this is
already better than just having a stack
allocated array because we now know the
size
of this array at any given time i could
simply pair this with a for loop like
this to
iterate through all of the members of
this actual array
simple as that however there are some
improvements we can actually make to
this function namely the fact that
this is clearly a value that we know at
compile time so why not let
other compile time tasks be able to take
advantage of that value
one example is a static assert maybe i
don't want
these arrays to be above a certain size
for some reason
so i could add a static assert that
simply checks to make sure that the size
of this array
is less than 10 and i can write it like
this i'll add a little message here as
well
and a static assert is an assert that
actually gets evaluated at compile time
this theoretically should work because i
mean we know the size at compile time
we're forced to specify the size of
compile time
however you can see here that it says
that the expression must have a constant
value and that's because this size
function simply
returns an integer what it should return
is a constant
expression by adding the const x per
keyword here we're specifying that this
actual function
can be evaluated at compile time and
since it can
you can see the assert here works fine
it also lets us create new arrays
from the size of that first array
because again
data.size is a function that can
actually be evaluated completely
during compile time and that's also the
reason why inside
the c plus plus array function lots of
their functions here as you can see
actually returns a constant expression
or rather most of these functions
are constant expressions okay so now
that we've done this
how do we iterate through this array and
actually pull out the values because at
the moment
even though i've got all of this stuff
going on there's no way for me to
actually
index this data now i could simply
return a pointer to this data but a
better way to do this is to implement
the index operator
and i can write a simple version of this
by just writing t then operator
open and close square bracket then int
index and then i'll simply return
m data at that index so this is kind of
like the
most simple straightforward way it has a
number of problems which we'll address
in a moment
but that's basically the idea so now
that we've written this we can simply
specify
the index of the data that we want to
read and you can see we now have the
ability to read this data and in fact we
can even print it to the console
if we want to okay great so what are the
problems
well first of all t is being returned by
value this may or may not be what you
want
the reason it may not be what you want
is because in this case we're just
returning integers
but what if we had a string would we
really want to completely copy the
string out every time we
use this index operator probably not we
simply want a read only reference to it
the other problem
here is that since this does actually
return by value and it makes a new copy
i can't do things like this because this
isn't a modifiable l value we're simply
returning a brand new copy of an integer
here there's nothing to assign to
there's no storage so because of that
we want to return a reference to this
actual type
even if it is something like an end
because even though we we're not really
interested in preventing copies for
integers we might be for the potential
other data types
but also by returning a reference it
lets us actually assign
into that index which is something that
we typically want to do
with an array such as this this poses
another problem though if this array
happens to be const for whatever reason
maybe we're
assigning it to like a const reference
or something like that we have our
array reference maybe we're passing it
into a function
and if we have this kind of const
reference here for the array
we obviously can't do this and we
wouldn't expect to be able to do this
because this is modifying the array and
it's constant so we shouldn't be doing
that
however you can see that we also can't
access it which is kind of a problem
because
const implies that it's read only we
should still be able to read the data
but not necessarily write the data this
we can easily fix by just adding another
version of this function which returns a
const
t reference and is also marked as const
this const over here means that we can
actually call this function
if the instance of array is constant
like it is for array reference
so this does not work which is what we
would expect but this does
and if we of course use the original
data which is not const
then everything works fine the final
real problem here is that we're using
int as the index
this lets us use negative numbers and
also might not be the same size on all
platforms so typically the sql standard
library likes to use size t
for these things if you go into array
and you take a look at their index
operator
you can see that they also use size type
here and size type is equal to
size t they have a lot of their own
definitions for a lot of these things at
least msvc's stl which is what we're
looking at here
has all of these various definitions
which just add a little bit of noise in
my opinion as to what is actually going
on here since you always have to look at
what these
are actually set to okay so now we have
a pretty good version of this
if we take a look at the version inside
array though you'll see that there is
also one other thing i mean largely it's
the same as our function i mean it's
also marked with no accept and
you know there's a few other various
flags going on here that we don't really
care about
at least for our basic example and then
this is this is
identical however we have this
preprocessor statement here the checks
to see if the container debug level
is greater than zero and if it is it
runs this stl verify thing that checks
the position versus the size so what
this is
is essentially an assert that checks to
see that this index
is within the accepted range so if we
were to add something like this
it would look like an if statement that
basically checks to see
whether or not index is less than the
actual size of the array which is
s and if this assert fails then we need
to do something like break the compiler
on this line this is an msvc way of
doing that this protects us because if
we accidentally loop over
something like this and we run the code
then it's actually going to break the
debugger on this line and tell us that
well we've done something wrong so that
we can debug the state of our program
this is not something that typically
gets included in release mode because
this extra check
just slows down our program and is
something that we would expect to catch
in debug mode anyway so that's that's
the extra check that we have in the stl
version of
the array class and something of course
that you might want to use however you
can see that this container debug level
macro actually makes sure that this does
not happen
in release mode okay cool so we'll we'll
just ignore that part
now size should also return a size t and
because it returns a size t
we should also make sure that our for
loop actually set to a size t
just to avoid some compiler warnings
i'll get rid of this and i'll clean up
our code a little bit more one other
thing that this class really needs is a
way to actually access the data within
it so in other words this will just
return
mdata and it will just return a pointer
to it you could also add a const version
of this that returns the data if you
wanted to and it would look something
like that what this enables you to do is
quickly for example set the memory to be
0 by just calling data.data writing 0 as
your value and then
the size of the array which is going to
be data.size times
size of int because that's the data type
that we've selected here this will set
all of the integers inside our array to
be zero by just simply setting
all of their memory to zero this isn't
really 100 required because you could
always
just simply take the first index of the
array and then grab the address of
that since this stack allocated array of
course is guaranteed to be
contiguous in memory so finally let's
see this in action what i'll do
is print every single index of our array
like so let's try it without the mem set
first to see the effect of that
all right cn.yet so that we pause our
console you can see we have just a bunch
of uninitialized memory here pretty
boring let's bring in the mem
set now all of the values inside our
array are set to zero
finally i'll maybe set index 1 to b5 and
index
4 to b8 so if we run this again
you can see we have zero five zero zero
eight so this seems to work and of
course if we wanted to
we could create an entirely different
array that maybe had
two strings string one we could set
equal to
journal like so and then string two we
could set
equal to c plus plus and then if we
basically have this exact same for loop
that we had before you can see that this
array also works
with strings so that is our basic array
class
you can see it's really tiny there are
still a lot of features that we would
want to add to this
namely the the biggest feature i think
is iterators
so at the moment we're having to write a
for loop like this but it would be
really nice if we could simply
have a for loop that looks something
like this where we could
get through our entire array just by
using a range based for loop like this
and to make that happen we actually need
to write an iterator which is a topic
for another video there are also some
other utility functions such as fill
and swab which we would probably want to
implement just to make dealing with our
array
slightly easier but that's going to be
it for today's
video okay so i hope you guys enjoyed
this video if you did please don't
forget to hit the like button
below obviously there's a lot of other
things we could add to this array class
and we will probably end up extending it
in some future videos like the iterators
and stuff like that
the core mechanics of a stack allocated
array are quite simple as you can
probably see and
this in and of itself is quite a
powerful data structure
that you can and should use frequently
throughout your code if you have any
other suggestions for data structures
for me to cover obviously i have a long
list of all of the popular ones but if
there's something specific that you want
me to cover or a different data
structure
that you want me to cover next please
let me know in the comment section below
i'll take a list probably
of all of your suggestions and we'll get
around to doing them as soon as possible
thank you guys once again for watching
do not forget to check out skillshare's
two months
of free premium using my link in the
description below and i will see
you next time goodbye
[Music]
you